Guide to the Milton Wolff Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.170
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Milton Wolff Photographs
1939-1960
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Wolff, Milton.
ALBA.PHOTO.170
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Milton (Milt) Wolff (1915-2008) was born in Brooklyn, NY to a working-class family. He left school at fifteen, found work in a Manhattan garment factory, and became politically active through membership in the Young Communist League. When the Civil War broke out in Spain he responded to a YCL appeal for volunteers and sailed for Europe, aged 21, in March 1937. He fought in the Battle of Brunete, at Belchite and in the unsuccessful assault at Fuentes del Ebro, and was promoted to captain during the battle of Teruel in January 1938. Wolff, aged 22, soon became the youngest commander of the Abraham Lincoln Battalion. He served in Burma, Italy, France and India in World War II, and continued to be active in a variety of left-wing causes throughout his life. The collection consists of 27 black and white photos and 7 contact sheets, mostly dating from the 1940s. Many of the images are of Milton Wolff speaking at meetings or demonstrations; others show him marching in demonstrations or with other Spanish Civil War veterans and guests at Abraham Lincolon Brigade anniversaries or other large gatherings. Prominent individuals pictured include Hugo Gellert, Burl Ives, Vito Marcantonio, John Gates, and Paul Robeson.
Provenance
The collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 27 black and white photos and 7 contact sheets, mostly dating from the 1940s. Many of the images are of Milton Wolff speaking at meetings or demonstrations; others show him marching in demonstrations or with other Spanish Civil War veterans and guests at Abraham Lincolon Brigade anniversaries or other large gatherings. Prominent individuals pictured include Hugo Gellert, Burl Ives, Vito Marcantonio, John Gates, and Paul Robeson.
Historical/Biographical Note
Milton (Milt) Wolff (1915-2008) was born in Brooklyn, NY to a working-class family. He left school at fifteen and worked in the New Deal 's Civilian Conservation Corps, 1933-1934. He later found work in a Manhattan garment factory and became politically active through membership in the Young Communist League. When the Civil War broke out in Spain he responded to a YCL appeal for volunteers and sailed for Europe, aged 21, in March 1937. He initially served as a medic and then saw action in a machine-gun unit of the Washington Battalion in the Battle of Brunete in July 1937. The depleted U.S. forces were merged with the Lincoln battalion and Wolf rose quickly through the ranks. He led his unit at Belchite and in the unsuccessful assault at Fuentes del Ebro, and was promoted to captain during the battle of Teruel in January 1938. As the Loyalist forces retreated across the Ebro, and regrouped for a final offensive, Wolff, aged 22, became commander of the Lincoln Battalion.
Wolff met Ernest Hemingway while on leave after Brunete, and forged with him an intense, lasting, and sometimes contentious friendship. Hemingway once described Wolff as being "as brave and as good a soldier as any that commanded battalions at Gettysburg." On his return from Spain Wolff immediately became active in organizing support for Loyalist refugees and opposition to the Franco regime, and he remained active in a host of left-wing causes. Over the years he campaigned for civil rights -- and especially for the integration of the Brooklyn Dodgers, organized aid to Cuba, demonstrated against the Vietnam War, and joined with other Lincoln veterans to send ambulances to Nicaragua.
In June 1942 he volunteered as a private in the U.S. Army infantry and went on to see action in Burma, where he received a field commission as a lieutenant, and other places. He served the OSS under General "Wild Bill" Donovan in building an intelligence network with Communist partisans in Italy, was a paratrooper in Italy, was a liaison to the Spanish Maquis in southern France, and served in India. After the War he found a variety of jobs, and developed his talents as a writer, painter, and photographer. Wolff made his home in California for many years, and died on January 14, 2008, only a few months before the dedication of the national monument to the U.S. volunteers in San Francisco.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into one series: I: Photographs, 1939-1960.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Milton Wolff Papers (ALBA 170) Other ALBA collections.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Demonstrations |z United States.; Germany (East); Demonstrations |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Demonstrations |y 1940-1950.; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Wolff, Milton.; Marcantonio, Vito, 1902-1954.; Quintanilla, Luis, 1895-1978; Gellert, Hugo, 1892-1985
- Series I: Photographs, 1939-1960.
  - Carnegie Hall: VALB Chorus Performing, [ca. 1945-1947] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Christmas Party, VALB: MW with [Norman Berkowitz as] Santa, Art Munday; Veterans' Children, Dec 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Demonstration, NYC: MW (center) with Actress Betty Garrett and Others (New York City Committee to Win the Peace), [circa 1946?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Demonstration, NYC: MW, Jack Bjoze, Nils Berg with Actors and Actresses (American Committee for Spanish Freedom), [circa 1946-1947] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Demonstration, NYC: MW Speaking, with Flags and Signs, May 1947 [?] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - East Germany: MW Speaking at Mass Rally, Berlin (photographs are of a tv screen), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - East Germany: MW Speaking at Microphone, Berlin, Sep 9, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gellert, Hugo, with Betty Shafran, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Johnson, Herschel, Interview: (l to r) MW, Paul Robeson, Schnee, Steele, Dr. Edward Barsky, May 22, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Madison Square Garden: MW at Podium, [1947?] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Marcantonio, Vito, with MW and Others, [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Meeting, "Lift the Embargo" Mecca Temple," NYC: John Gates (speaking), Dr. Langley, Dr. Edith Summerskill, MW, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Meeting: MW Speaking at Podium, [circa 1945-1947] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Meeting [?] with Polish General: MW, Angel Guest, Jack Bjoze; Group of Veterans' Wives, [circa 1945-1947?] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Portrait: MW in World War II Uniform, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Quintanilla, Luis, Dinner for (Hotel Roosevelt, NYC): MW with Diplomats, Nov 21, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Briagde (VALB) Anniversary Gathering: MW Speaking and with Others, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Wellman, Peggy, with Veterans' Children, [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Wives of Veterans, at a Party, [early 1940s] (Box 1, Folder 19)